Guide to the World War I Pamphlet Collection 1901-1944 (bulk 1914-1919)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
- United States - Foreign Politics, Pre-war: Philippines (in English), 1916; Seaman, Louis Livingstone. The Holier Than Thou Policy of the President. Philadelphia: [s. n.], 1916. (2 copies) (Box-folder 35/14)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Anglo-American, Pre-war (in English), 1914-1915; Schulze, Frederick A. England and Its Relation to the Present European War, Causes, Motives, Results. Hoboken? N.J.: s.n.], 1914.; Cockerell, Douglas. An English Industrial Town in Time of War. Boulder, Colo.?: T.D.A. Cockerell?, 1914.; Official Report. Washington D.C.: 1915. (2 copies); Buckley, Edward. England Responsible for the European War. Chicago: 1915. (Box-folder 35/15)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Anglo-American, Pre-war (in English), 1915; Hale, William Bayard. American Rights & British Pretensions on the Seas; The Facts and the Documents, Official and Other, Bearing Upon the Present Attitude of Great Britain Toward the Commerce of the United States. New York: R.M. McBride & Co, 1915. (Box-folder 36/1)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Anglo-American, Pre-war (in English), 1916; Philosophus. The War: What Is England Doing? Pamphlets on World War I, v. 6. London: Jas. Truscott & Son, 1916.; The Case against Armed Merchantmen: Timely Reprints from the New York Press. New York: S.n, 1916. (2 copies); Barron, Clarence W. The War for Humanity: An Address Before the Canadian Club of Toronto, Series K, No. 1. Wall Street Journal Leaflets, 1916. (Box-folder 36/2)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Anglo-American, Wartime (in English), 1917; Beer, George Louis. The English-Speaking Peoples, Their Future Relations and Joint International Obligations. New York: Macmillan Co, 1917.; Towne, Charles Hanson. The Balfour Visit: How America Received Her Distinguished Guest; and the Significance of the Conferences in the United States in 1917. New York, N.Y.: G.H. Doran Co, 1917.; Page, Walter H. The Union of Two Great Peoples A Speech by W.H. Page, LL. D., American Ambassador to England, Delivered at Plymouth, August 4th, 1917. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1917. (Box-folder 36/3)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Anglo-American, Wartime (in English), 1918; A Declaration of Interdependence Commemoration in London in 1918 of the 4th of July, 1776: Resolutions and Addresses at the Central-Hall, Westminster. New York: Library of War Literature, 1918.; The Common Cause: Britain's Part in the Great War. New York: Library of War Literature, 1918.; America's Tribute to Britain: A Celebration in Honor of Great Britain's Achievement in the Great World War. Washington, D. C.: 1918. (part of the this is missing) (Box-folder 36/4)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Armenian-American (in English), 1919-1921; Main, John Hanson Thomas. America's Duty in Armenia. New York?: s.l, 1919.; Gerard, James W. Armenia's Call to America. The American Committee for the Independence of Armenia, 1919.; The Armenian National Union of America. A Memorandum on Armenia: Presented to the Government of the United States. New York: 1921. (Box-folder 36/5)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Belgo-American (in English), 1915-1916 and undated; Commission for Relief in Belgium. Calorie Production and C.R.B. Analyses of the Common Foods, n. d.; Hoch! Der Kaiser; or me und Gott. n. d. (leaflet explaining how Emperor William manages the universe); Kilmarnock, John. "The Case of Belgium" Reviewed. Washington D.C., 1915. (2 copies); Royce, Josiah. The Duties of Americans in the Present War: Address Delivered at Tremont Temple, Sunday, January 30, 1916. Boston, Mass: Citizens' League for America and the Allies, 1916.; "The Enslavement of Belgians": A Protest. New York?: s.n, 1916.; Chapple, Joe Mitchell. A Vision: After the War, the United States of the World. Boston, 1916. (two copies) (Box-folder 36/6)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Belgo-American (in English), 1917-1921; United States, and Brand Whitlock. The Deportations: Statement by the American Minister to Belgium. London: T.F. Unwin, 1917. (2 copies); Carnoy, Albert Joseph. The Restoration of Belgium and Her Future. The University of California Chronicle, 1919.; Stillemans, Joseph F. Belgium's Contribution to America's Making. New York: Belgian Committee of "America's making", 1921. (Box-folder 36/7)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Franco-American, Wartime (in English), 1917; Le Petit, Nicholas. Wake Up, Young America, Time Has Come for Thy Revenge. New York: 1917. (Box-folder 36/8)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Franco-American, Wartime (in French), 1917-1918; Mirman, Léon. La Marseillaise des États-Unis. Nancy: Rigot, 1917. (book of poetry); United States. L'Effort Américain, Avril 1917-Avril 1918. Compte Rendu Officiel De La Première Année De Guerre Préparé Par Le Bureau De L'Information Publique À Washington, D.C. 1918. (2 copies) (Box-folder 36/9)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Franco-American, Post-war (in English), 1920-1922; Hacket, Edmund Francis. What France Did for Us. New York: La France, 1920.; Ferree, Barr. The Chronology of the Cathedral Churches of France. New York: 1922.; Lippmann, Walter. France and the European Settlement an address by M. Walter Lippmann before the Foreign Policy Association. New York: 1922. (Box-folder 36/10)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Germany-American, Pre-war (in English), 1914; Church, Samuel Harden. The American Verdict on the War. A Reply to the Manifesto of the German Professors. London: "The Times" Pub. Co, 1914.; Briesen, Arthur von. Who Brought About the War in Europe? Is Germany to Blame for Disregarding Belgian Treaty? New York: New York Times, 1914.; Lewis, Roger. Joint Declaration. 1914. (2 copies) (Box-folder 36/11)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Germany-American, Pre-war (in English), 1915; Schweitzer, Hugo. Can Germany Be Starved into Submission? New York: German American Literary Defense Committee, 1915.; Gordon, Hanford L. The Unholy War on Germany. Los Angeles: 1915.; Fullerton, George Stuart. Why the German Nation Has Gone to War: An American to Americans. München: Hans Sachs, 1915. (2 copies); Fineshriber, W. H. In Defense of Germany: Read at Meeting of March 1, 1915. 1915. (Box-folder 36/12)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Germany-American, Wartime (in English), 1917; Johnson, Douglas Wilson. Plain Words from America; A Letter to a German Professor. London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1917.; The Committee on Public Information. War Information Series, No. 1. War Message and Facts Behind It: Annotated Text of President Wilson's Message, April 2, 1917. Washington: Govt. print. off, 1917.; Wilson, Woodrow, and Wallace Notestein. The President's Flag Day Address, With Evidence of Germany's Plans. Washington: U.S. Govt. Print. Off, 1917. (2 copies) (Box-folder 36/13)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Germany-American, Wartime (in English), 1917-1918; Andrews, C. C. Germany's Responsibility for the War. St. Paul, Minn: 1917.; The Committee on Public Information. War Message and Facts Behind It, Delivered Before Congress April 2, 1917, with Annotations, Giving the Leading Facts on Which the Rupture with Germany Was Developed, the Issues in International Law, and Contrasting the Spirit of Prussianism and Americanism. Washington: Govt. print. off, 1917.; Manufacturers' Record, Baltimore. Damning Revelations of Germany's Turpitude; A Confession from a Partner in a Nation's Crime. Baltimore, Md: Manufacturers Record Pub. Co, 1918. (Box-folder 36/14)
- United States - Foreign Relations: India-American (in English), 1918; United States. Interpretation of War Statutes Bulletin No. 159: Hindu Conspiracy Case. Washington: G.P.O., 1918. (Box-folder 36/15)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Italo-American, Wartime (in English and Italian), 1917-1918; Warren, Whitney. The Just Claims of Italy; The Question of the Trentin, of Trieste and of the Adriatic (21 Maps and Diagrams). 1917.; Gay, Harry Nelson. L'Italia e gli Stati Uniti: 24 Maggio 1918. Genova: Pietro Pellas fu L., 1918.; Gay, Harry Nelson. L'America del Nord per la vittoria della civilta: 4 Luglio 1918. Genova: Pietro Pellas fu L., 1918. (Box-folder 36/16)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Italo-American, Post-war (in English), 1919-1922; Gigliotti, Cairoli. The Truth about Fiume and Dalmatia. Chicago: 1919.; Hazelton, Henry Isham. Fiume: The Superlatively Italian City. Chicago: 1919.; The American Mission to Rome for the Bestowal of the Congressional Medal of Honor Upon the Unknown Italian Soldier, January 1922. Rome: The Library for Amer. Studies in Italy, 1922. (Box-folder 36/17)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Japanese-American (in English), 1914-1919; Asiatic Institute. Japanese Declarations and Assurances Respecting Participation in the European War in the Pacific. New York: Asiatic Institute Press, 1914.; Iyenaga, T. The Case of Japan in the Peace Treaty. New York: Reprinted by League to Enforce Peace, 1919. (Box-folder 36/18)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Lithuanian-American (in English), 1917; Do You Feel the Draft? 1917. (Box-folder 36/19)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Polish-American (in English), 1919-1923 and undated; Stevens, Frederick W. A Little of the Story of Poland. Michigan:; National Department of the Polish Central Relief Committee of America. Letter discussing the Polish question. n. d.; Poland: A New Field for American Enterprises. n. d. (typed report on Poland's industrial development); Vorzimer, J. An Open Letter to Mr. Nathan Strauss. New York: 1919.; Polish bureau of information, New York. Poland After Five Years; Quinquennial Review of the Activities of the Republic of Poland. New York: Polish bureau of information, 1923. (Box-folder 36/20)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Russo-American, Wartime (in English), 1915-1918; Jackson, Luis. Russia Dominates the World. War pamphlets, v. 1. Montclair, N.J.: Percival Mullikin Co, 1915. (2 copies); London, Meyer. The Russian Revolution and the World War: Speech of the Hon. Meyer London of New York in the House of Representatives, Friday, June 29, 1917. Washington: G.P.O., 1917.; Browne, Louis Edgar. New Russia in the Balance, How Germany's Designs May Be Defeated and Russian Democracy Preserved. [Chicago]: Chicago daily news, 1918.; Full Texts of Secret Treaties As Revealed at Petrograd. New York: The New York Evening Post, 1918. (Box-folder 37/1)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Russo-American, Post-war (in English), 1920-1922; Hughes, Rupert. The Third Russia. New York: New York Times Book Review and Magazine: 1920.; Haines, Anna J. Thru the Valley of the Shadow of Death: A Journey among fifteen million people in the Volga Valley of Russia whom famine is destroying. Philadelphia: American Friends Service Committee, 1920.; American-Russian Society. Russia, an American Problem. New York: The Society, 1921.; Sack, A. J. Two Policies Towards Russia. Russian Information Bureau, 1921.; Parker, Alton B. Shall Soviet Russia be Recognized? Report Submitted by a Special Committee to the National Civic Federation and Transmitted by its President, Alton B. Parker...on January 10, 1922. New York: 1922. (Box-folder 37/2)
- United States - Foreign Relations: Russo-American, Post-war (in English), 1923; Pallen, Conde B. Why The Russian Soviets Should Not Be Recognized. New York City: The National Civic Federation, 1923. (Box OS 43)
- United States - Military: Campaigns/Battles (in English), 1927; Freeman, Walter. World War Chart of Major Operations. From the (Re-checked) Report of the Secretary of War, 1926. Pasadena, Calif: 1927. (Box OS 44)
- United States - Military: Campaigns / Battles (in English), 1928; Dickson, Thomas Jefferson. The World War; Major Tactics of the Greatest Battle in History, July 18 to November 11, 1918. 1928. (Box-folder 37/3)
- United States - Military: Caricatures / Humor (in English), 1917-1919 and undated; Lest We Forget. F. Company, 2nd Division, 23rd Infantry, A. E. F. n.d.; Yank Talk: A Review of A.E.F. Humor - Trench and Billet. Paris: The Lafayette Publishing Co., 1917.; Cumming, John P. More Yank Talk: A Review of A.E.F. Humor: Trench and Billet. Paris: Lafayette Pub. Co, 1919. (Box-folder 37/4)
- United States - Military: Caricatures / Humor (in English), 1918; American Expeditionary Forces. The Martian. Vol. 1, No. 17. [Mars-sur-Allier], France: Hospital Center, American Expeditionary Forces, 1918. (Box-folder OS 45)
- United States - Military: Conscription and Selective Service (in English), 1917-1919; Local Board for the County of Rice. "The Honor Roll", Rice County, Minnesota. List of Names of Persons Registered ... for the Selective Draft, Showing Serial Numbers, Names, and Addresses. Minnesota: Journal Faribault, 1917.; United States Department of Justice. Interpretation of War Statutes: Bulletins. [Washington, D.C.]: G.P.O., 1917-1919. (various bulletins relating to the draft and selective service) (Box-folder 37/5)
- United States - Military: Espionage Act and Sedition (in English), 1918-1919; United States Department of Justice. Interpretation of War Statutes: Bulletins. [Washington, D.C.]: G.P.O., 1918-1919. (various bulletins espionage of American-German citizens) (Box-folder 37/6)
- United States - Military: Insignia (in English), 1919; Divisional Insignia of the American Army. Chicago: Meyer Both Co., 1919.; Our Country's Defenders: Souvenir for Americans and their Posterity. Kansas City, MO: The Smith-Grieves Company, 1919. (book of military insignia stickers) (Box-folder 37/7)
- United States - Military: Minority Soldiers (in English), 1918-1930; Hampton in War Time. Hampton, Virginia: Press of the Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute, 1918.; Boston Hampton Committee. A Brief Sketch of the Record of the American Negro and Indian in the Great War. S.l: s.n.], 1919.; War Camp Community Service (U.S.). War Camp Community Service and the Negro Soldier. 1920.; Marshall, N. B. The Providential Armistice: A Volunteer's Story, Military Sketch of Captain Napoleon B. Marshal. Washington D. C.: Liberty League, 1930. (Box-folder 37/8)
- United States - Military: Personal Narratives and Correspondence (in English), 1919-1929; Ridenour-Baker and the World War, 1917-1919. Kansas City, Mo: Ridenour-Baker, 1919. (letters between discharged American soldiers to American soldiers fighting in Europe); Blumenstein, Christian. Whiz Bang! Buffalo, N.Y.: Christian Blumenstein, 1927.; Fritchey, Alfred James. Two Battles. California: 1929. (Box-folder 37/9)
- United States - Military: Personal Narratives and Correspondence (in English), 1931-1932; Sibley, Eugene. Comrades of the Highway. Detroit: Premier Press, 1931. (2 copies); Pilcher, J. Mitchell. Randy, Forgotten Man of the World War. Tacoma: Economy Publishers, 1932. (2 copies) (Box-folder 37/10)
- United States - Military: Regulations (in English), 1917-1918; Director General of Transportation. American Expeditionary Forces. Transportation Department. Rules Governing Train Operation Issued by Director General of Transportation. Effective June 1st, 1918. Tours: impr. de Mame, 1918.; United States, and Thomas W. Hardwick. Hearings Before the Committee on Military Affairs, United States Senate, Sixty-Fifth Congress, First Session, on S. 2717, a Bill Prescribing Rules for the Government and Regulation of the Land and Naval Forces During the Period of the Existing War with Germany. [August 31, 1917]. Washington: Govt. Print. Off, 1917. (Box-folder 37/11)
- United States - Military: Service Histories and Pictorials (in English), 1919 and undated; New Orleans Chapter, Military Order of the World War. Lieutenant Nelson and his Indispensable Fours (Typed Letter). n. d. (two newpaper clippings attached to the letter); Ruggles, Logan Elsworth, and Owen W. Norton. History of the Von Steuben and the Part She Played in the Great War. Hoboken, N.J.: Ship History Pub. Co, 1919.; United States. Victory Parades of the First Division, United States Army: Official Souvenir Program Authorized by the War Department, New York, Sept. 10, 1919, Washington, D.C., Sept. 17, 1919. Washington, D.C.: Army Pictorial, Surgeon General, 1919. (Box-folder 37/12)
- United States - Military: Service Histories and Pictorials (in English), 1922-1924; Cunningham, Dick. Cunningham of the Daily Press: A Romance and Authentic History of the Recent World War. New York: Rose-Bray Publishing Company, 1922.; Davis, Arthur Kyle. Virginians of Distinguished Service of the World War. Richmond, Va: Pub. by order of the Executive Committee, 1923.; 308th Engineers Veteran Association. The "History" of Our History: 308th and Programme, Third Annual Reunion. Ohio: 1923.; Fifth Reunion, Old Hickory 30th Division: Official Souvenir Program. Charleston, S. C.: Walkter, Evans & Cogswell Co., 1924. (Box-folder 37/13)
- United States - Military: Service Histories and Pictorials (in English), 1927-1928; Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Virginia Polytechnic Institute in the World War. Blacksburg, Va: Virginia polytechnic institute, 1927.; McCrea, Henry S. A Souvenir of Service in War and in Peace. Massachusetts: 1928. (Box-folder 37/14)
- United States - Military: Soldiers' Affairs (in English), 1918 and undated; Program (Engineer School, Washington Barracks D, Central Map Reproduction Plant). n. d. (graduation program for the Washington Barracks Detachment of the 472nd Engineers); The Making of Trench and Camp. "The Soldiers' Own Paper". New York: Trench & Camp, n. d.; Recommendations: Dry and White Zone Needed, Ask Allies for Soldier Protection, Y.M.C.A.-Red Cross Commended. n. d.; Crandall, Charles Henry. War Songs for the Boys in Khaki. Stamford, Conn: [Charles H. Crandall, 1918.; Camp Joseph E. Johnston (Jacksonville, Fla.), and Abraham Finkel. Roster and History at Conclusion of World War for Democracy of Groups One and Two of Camp Joseph E. Johnston, Jacksonville, Florida. 1918. (Box-folder 37/15)
- United States - Military: Training and War Camps (in English), 1917-1918; War Camp Community Service (U.S.). Keep 'em Smiling! [New York]: War Camp Community Service, 1917.; Amherst College. Amherst in the War, Volume 7, Bulletin No. 3. Amherst, Mass: Amherst College, 1918. (2 copies); University of Oregon Leaflet Series. Second Officers' Training Camp. For Civilians--Military Training on the Plattsburg Model. Four Weeks--August 3 to August 31, 1918. Eugene, Oregon: University of Oregon, 1918. (Box-folder 38/1)
- United States - Military: U-boat Warfare (in English), 1917-1918; Naval Consulting Board & War Committee of Technical Societies. The Submarine and Kindred Problems: Bulletin No. 1. New York: Naval Consulting Board of the United States, 1917.; Naval Consulting Board & War Committee of Technical Societies. The Enemy Submarine: Bulletin No. 2. New York: Naval Consulting Board of the United States, 1918. (Box-folder 38/2)
- United States - National Security League (in English), 1915-1918 and undated; Bill, Charles Alfred. How to Form and Run a Flying Squadron of Speakers. New York: The National Security League, n. d.; Committee on Physical Reserve. A Manual of Physical Exercise, prepared for general use. New York City: National Security League, n. d. (2 copies; 2nd and 4th edition); National Security League. Its Accomplishments in the Past and Its Present and Future Activities, Briefly Summarized. New York City: The National Security League, Inc., n. d.; Keep, O. T. Home Defense Leagues: Suggestions for their Organization. New York City: The National Security League, n. d.; The National Security League. How to Form a Branch and What To Do. New York: The National Security League, n. d. (2 copies); Menken, S. Stanwood. To the Chairmen and Secretaries of Branches of the National Security League: New York: The National Security League, n. d.; National Security League. Constitution and By-Laws for Branches of National Security League, Inc. New York, N.Y.: National Security League, National Headquarters, 1915.; National Security League. Report of Director of Branches. Read at the Annual Meeting. New York: The National Security League, 1916.; National Security League. The National Security League, Inc.: What It Is and Why, What It Has Done and Is Doing: a National Defense Catechism for the Busy Man or Woman. New York, N.Y.: The League, 1917.; West, Henry L. Synopsis of an Address by Henry L. West. Washington D. C.: The National Security League, 1917.; Menken, S. Stanwood. Report of the Chairman of the Executive Committee, Delivered at the Annual Meeting. New York: The National Security League, 1917.; National Security League. Annual Meeting of the National Security League held at Hotel Astor, New York City. New York [N.Y.]: The League, 1917.; Lane, Franklin Knight. Message of Hon. Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of the Interior: To the Speakers' Training Camp and Conference at Chautauqua Institution, Chautauqua, N.Y., Under the Auspices of the National Security League, July 5, 1917. S.l: The National Security League, 1917. (2 copies); National Security League. Its Past, Present and Future Work. New York: The National Security League, 1918. (Box-folder 38/3)
- United States - National Security League: Patriotism through Education (in English), 1916 and undated; National Security League. Teachers' Patriotic Leaflets, Volume 1: Committee on Patriotism through Educations of the National Security League. New York City: The National Security League, n. d. (2 copies); Oliver, Frederick Scott. Policy and Armaments. New York City: The National Security League, n. d.; George, Alice Nelson Vaut. The Teaching of Patriotism in Home and School An Address at the National Security Congress, Under the Auspices of the National Security League, Washington, January 20, 1916. New York, N.Y.: National Security League, 1916. (Box-folder 38/4)